"Hello. Welcome back to lamrim.
Today we're going to do a review of the entire course.
This is good for me... I'd like to do a review myself.
In this format, when you do the classes separately
and then do them at different times,
you kind of lose the flow of the entire teaching.
I thought today it would be nice if we went back
to the beginning and went through the entire flow of the
lamrim teaching that we had.
I'm going to make this flow based on idims, on images of ideas
that we use in ACI teacher training.
ACI teachers are supposed to
be able to look at one of these pictures
and identify the idea behind it.
I'm guessing, Tim, how many did we say there would be? A thousand or something like that?
How many?
500, something like that. So taking the exam is pretty easy,
taking someone's exam just on pictures.
So we're just throwing these pictures at you.
So I challenge you during this review,
when we show a picture,
I'll give you a second and see if you can
remember what it was about  this picture?
Okay, and that's a great overview of the
whole course that we're doing. Okay, here we go...
The first picture, Mr. Seiji.
This picture should remind you
that we're in the middle of the practice
for people of average ability,
and what they're striving for is nirvana.
They're trying to get out of the wheel of life, out of all the suffering for themselves personally. This is where
the Buddha taught the three trainings
that will help you achieve personal nirvana.
The third training is understanding emptiness, understanding the pen. The
second training is meditation.
At a deep level, those two can only be done in a quiet place,
at a certain time of day, when you really focus on your meditation mat.
At a deep level, those two trainings should be done
at certain times of the day.
But this one, the foundation for those two, is being kind to other people.
You can call it morality.
You can call it an ethical way of life,
but ultimately it means being kind to other people.
This is the foundation
that is always available to us throughout the day.
This is one of the three extraordinary  Buddhist training
to help us achieve nirvana.
And it's available to us all day long.
So, in this picture,
you can see Seiji helping Geshe Michael figure out his computer.
It's one of the nicest things young people can do for older people. The
next picture; see if you can remember what that picture was? Did
you guess?
This woman is paying taxes. What does this woman become in the lam-rim system?
That makes her a
Dharma master. When I say "Dharma master," or "tantric master,"
I know what picture you have in your mind.
It's some big lama on a throne, and he has a big yellow hat.
Maybe they're ringing a bell and a little drum, and they...
And you think, "Oh, that's a Dharma master."  This is a real Dharma master."
Or you think about this old drawing of Nagarjuna,
and it's... it's all kind of mystical.
In the lamrim, what we learned
about this woman, she
has two children, she's married,
and she's a Dharma master. She's a real Dharma master.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, "Don't think that a Dharma master has to sit on a throne,
reciting some tantric ritual.
What is this woman doing?
She pays taxes.
To be honest, it is very difficult to deal with taxes in my country.
It can take weeks to do your taxes and
to really do them accurately, to
do them absolutely honestly,
to pay every penny that you owe.
This makes her...
She has the first of the extraordinary trainings of a good person;
kindness to other people.
This makes her a true Dharma master.
Forget about those photos where you see llamas wearing big hats
and ringing bells.  Okay, that's simple.
Anyone can do it.
It's hard to be kind to people,
and it's hard to maintain your morals, to maintain your ethics
.
Next.
I'll give you a minute.  Do you remember what we are talking about?  The
lamrim quote was tsul khrim den pe ge lon yo tang den (TSUL KHRIMS LDAN PA'I DGE SLONG 'OD DANG LDAN)
A person who truly keeps his commitments,
truly keeps his Buddhist principles, especially the 10 principles,
he shines, he truly shines.
A person who makes a healthy, modest, and discreet effort to fulfill his obligations
to preserve ten good karmas and
be kind to other people has a
calm expression on his face and is
radiant.
When he walks into a room, you know it.
Everyone starts to feel better, like Tim and Sage.
This is the light of the whole world.
Buddha said: "These people are the light of the world."
There is a Christian expression:
"Don't put a candle under a basket, let the world see your happy face."
And this is the true guiding light for the whole world.  The
next picture is #4
This is the rock I went to with my wife Veronica for her birthday during this lamrim.
They talked about sunset, which in Tibetan means NUB PA.
It also means "west" because the sun sets in the West;
NUB PA means
the sun is setting and is a very sad verb.
This is a very sad idea in Dharma, The
most famous place is at the end of Abhidharmakosha;  Treasury of Supreme Wisdom.
The Treasury of the Supreme Knowledge of Master Vasabhandu and he says:
"The Sun of Dharma, the light of Dharma, will set in this world."
We will lose the light of Dharma in this world.  This world will be plunged into darkness.
After a certain amount of time, the
Buddha's teachings will disappear from this world.
At first they disappear from people's minds, but they are still in libraries.
These books are still in libraries.  Possibly in libraries that John Brady hasn't found yet.
And then, later, they will also disappear from the libraries, and then they will disappear forever.
I put this picture here because Pabongkha Rinpoche made a special point, he said,
"If you cannot fulfill your commitments, if you cannot maintain good behavior towards other people,
then it can be said that the Dharma has left this world."
The light of Dharma has left this world within you.
The sun has set in your breasts,
which would be very sad if we did not keep our vows.
Next picture.
We called this retreat "Love in the Time of Virus".
The point is that in a very difficult time in the world,
if you keep your commitments,
if you treat other people well,
when everything is scary and frightening and the virus is spreading.
We don't know where, we don't know how, and
we don't know how many people will die.
If you do something nice for other people during these difficult times,
it is much, much more powerful.
He mentioned, if you remember, the 5-star Buddha Paradise,
it's like the perfect place.
It's easy to be a good person, all the people there are good.
This is not a great achievement.                                            It is not that important
and the seed is not that strong
to be good in the company of good people.
Be kind when people attack you, when people are afraid.
When people treat each other badly and being the only person
who stands up and shares things in difficult times
is an extremely pure person.
This is great karma.  This is incredible karma, much more powerful.
I think this virus is a very good time and a
very good chance for all of us to show
- are we really Buddhists?   Are we really practicing the Bodhisattva path?
Can we help others even when things are really hard?
Next picture.
This one is hard to remember, it's hard for me to remember it.
I'll give you a second to think about what this picture is about.
Pabongkha Rinpoche quoted some books
with very, very common endings across different books.
He quoted the famous phrase lobsang gyel we ten pa (BLO BZANG RGYAL BA'I BSTAN PA) chik (CIG)
may the teachings of the victorious
Lobsang Drakpa Je Tsongkhapa be
spread throughout this world.
You think we should go online.
We must translate this lamrim into many languages.
We must try to reach as many people as possible with the good word.
This is the end of the prayer and we must exit this lamrim video class
and we must start sharing the Dharma with other people.
We must spread Dharma in the world.
In this part of the lamrim, Pabongka Rinpoche said,
“The place where you should spread the Dharma is here, in your own heart.”
Don't think that spreading Dharma means trying to translate videos
into other languages ​​or anything like that.  This is a very important dissemination of Dharma.
But he says, "If you spread it in your own heart,
then of course it will spread beyond you, because peace comes from your heart,
from your heart chakra, actually.
Next picture #7
Try to remember what that picture was about. I'll give you a second.
This is my favorite theme;
to have a personal relationship with another person, like these two people have.
In my opinion, and in Tantra, it is one of the happiest things that can happen to you.
It is one of the greatest things that can happen to you.
Anyone can tell you the reason why the whole world is looking for a partner -
it makes people happy.
It is a great happiness when things go well.
It is one of the greatest happinesses you can have, but
you know and I know when things don't go well -
it is one of the greatest misfortunes in life.
Why is this relevant to this course in particular?
If your morals are good -
that is the happiest thing in your life.
And if you violate your morals, that is the same thing that will  you unhappy.
It's like having a good woman or man who is your partner,
the same person who makes you completely happy
can also make you completely unhappy.
So in this case, the Vinaya, your personal practice of kindness,
good behavior, is compared to a partner
who can either make you the best in your life
or the worst in your life – one and the same person.
Next Idima 8.
This one was difficult. See if you can remember?
I'll take a sip of my green drink.
Thank you, Vimala.
This actually means breaking your commitments.
Pulling a weed means breaking your commitments.
Why does destroying this plant violate your commitments?
If you are a gardener, you know that you must pull the weed
before the seeds ripen.
If you wait until the seeds ripen
and then pull the plant,
you will scatter about a thousand seeds.
Next month or next year, you will have thousands of weeds growing.
So you must attack these weeds in advance.
This refers to a very radical statement
that the Buddha made.  It is
better to die
than to break your commitments. Why?
When you break your commitments,
you set in motion seeds
that will continue to be sown for many lifetimes.
If you die, you destroy one body-mind complex.
If you die, you destroy one very useful temple, the
physical temple and mind. You lose one.
But if you break your commitments,
you lose many body-mind complexes.
You destroy your body and mind over many lifetimes.
And you are, as it were, setting in motion seeds
that will destroy many lifetimes.
The Buddha said, "It is better to die than to break your vows."
And he was not being metaphorical at all. He was speaking very literally
when he said that. It is better to die than to break your commitments.
There is a joke in lam-rim.
We take a vow never to give up  bodhicitta, even at the cost of our own lives.
There's a famous saying that we wait our whole lives for some evil people to
put us in jail
.
They come with a knife and say, "Give up your bodhisattva vows or die today."
Then we say,
"I choose death."
And they kill us.
I think we've all been waiting for this since we took our vows.
We're all waiting for these guys to show up with knives and threaten us.
But in reality, we are the guys with knives. We threaten our bodhisattva vows every day.
We have to make that decision every day when we decide whether or not to keep our vows carefully.
It's hard to find those guys who would put you in jail and say,
"I'll kill you if you don't give up your bodhisattva commitments."
Next picture.
See if you can remember. I'll give you a minute to try to remember.
That was a mention...
We have a team of translators called Mixed Nuts,
and we were translating an old Vinaya text, the
vows of monks and nuns.
They were talking about vows, about a tradition that we shouldn't...
...when you become a monk or a nun, they give you your monastic robes,
they give you a small Buddhist statue,
and a strainer.
And in ancient India, it was believed that you should always carry this strainer with you.
When you drink water from a stream,
you should first strain the water to make sure you don't kill any small insects.
We mentioned a famous tradition in the Vinaya,
if a couple of monks go down to the water,
down to the stream for water,
then they should choose the most responsible monk to test the water.
Don't choose the guy who doesn't care about bugs. Try to find a guy who likes bugs.
And let him test the water, because he'll be more careful.
What's the point of that?
We were talking about peculiar ecological vows,
where monks and nuns  You shouldn't even pick the green leaves from the
plants because they are the homes of tiny creatures.
This means respecting even the smallest vows,
taking them very seriously because the results multiply exponentially. It
's also important to keep your morality on a very subtle level,
on a very subtle level, and not become meticulous.
If I were going to write bodhisattva commitments,
I would write an additional bodhisattva vow about
not becoming meticulous about bodhisattva vows.
There is nothing more annoying than
a person who tells you that he will keep his vows and
that's why they look like jerks today.
Keep your vows gently. Keep them joyfully. Don't overdo it.
Don't bother other people with your vows because vows shouldn't bother other people.
Keep small vows, keep them quietly. Keep them privately, don't advertise it.
There is a saying in Islam, "The left hand should not speak to the right hand about  What she does."
What it means is, don't advertise your vows. Just keep them quietly.
Keep them on a very subtle level.
Next picture.
This is the idea that being kind to other people
is like planting a tree.
Today I went to the Peach Tree Cafe
to check out something, and
Stanley, Alison, and I planted a peach tree there
when we first started the Peach Tree morning show.
And I want to tell you guys, three peaches have ripened this week, so
we have peaches now. What
it means is, take care of your core practice.
Take care of the root and plant good karma
by keeping your vows, by being kind to other people.
Then it will grow into a tree.
And this peach tree that we planted
five months ago or so is
already bearing a lot of fruit.
If you hadn't taken care of it when it was tiny, you wouldn't have anything.
If you take care of your core Buddhist practice,
which means being kind to others  people,
then there will be thousands and thousands and thousands of fruits.
They will appear, it will grow
into a huge... it will grow into a tree
and it will bear peaches every year, for many years you will have peaches.
Take care.... protect....
this child carefully protected the sprout.
Protect your morality.
Next picture.
If I remember correctly, there were four conditions
that could cause you to break your commitments.
If you took the bodhisattva commitments
or you took the Vinaya Pratimoksha commitments,
or even if you took the Diamond Way tantric commitments.
I think there were four.. Pabongka Rinpoche went over... maybe even more....
anyway, there were certain conditions
that contributed to breaking your vows.
If you want to break your vows, there are a few specific ways to do it.
Here is the first one.
If you don't know what your vows are,
then this is a good way to break them. If you want to break them,
then don't study them and,
one of them really irritates me,  I have a lot of Dharma irritants, and they are
teachers who give initiations, initiations to the masses,
and they don’t explain to the people taking the initiation
that they have just taken vows.
There are hundreds of vows that you took when you received initiation,
and you will definitely break them if you don’t know them.
It is the teacher’s responsibility
to teach you your vows before you receive initiation.
If they don’t offer to teach you, I would not take initiation from them.
The best way to break your vows, the first way, is not to know them.
Read the recipe before you start cooking.
That’s what Veronica tells me every time I cook.
Next picture.
This woman says, “Yeah, it’s not such a big deal.”
It’s a vow not to cut green plants without prayer,
okay, that’s an extreme. It’s a little excessive, it’s not that big of a deal.
It’s just a couple of bugs
that sometimes use this leaf as a roof.
It’s not that big of a deal.
The second great way to break your vows
is to have this attitude:
“Oh, this one doesn’t  so important, I keep big ones."
Next.
If we get a kleshe, that is, if we get some kind of negativity
that swirls in our minds, that's a great way to break your vows.
Being mad at someone else or
being obsessed with something or money or
being addicted to our Netflix at night.
.... by the way, there's nothing wrong with watching Netflix, but I'm talking about
not hurting someone else because you want to come home and watch your Netflix. That's the problem.
It's called a gang fight.
What's the story?
Go to the biggest guy on the opposing side.
Find out who the leader is on the other side
and don't talk, don't negotiate, don't yell at each other,
go up to him and hit him over the head.
And then the whole other side will collapse.
Identify your worst bad habit
and deal with it first. That's the way to keep your vows.
Next.
By the way, at my age,
I'll tell you how old I am,
but all this young love stuff
– they're so ridiculous from my age's perspective.
I can say this from experience, because I've had it.
But this thing about:
"Oh, she's the most beautiful woman in the world.
He's the most handsome guy in the world."
First of all, my older brother,
he said the funniest thing. "Do you like this girl?" he asked. "Yes," I said. "Do
you want to spend your whole life with her?" "Yes," I said.
He said, "Check her mother first.
Look at what her mom looks like?" I said mom looks terrible. She's overweight, she looks tired, and she looks terrible.
And he said, "Well, what do you think she looked like in the beginning?"
So think about it?
If you're attached to a person's appearance,
or anything physical, or anything not very important about a person.
That will change, and you'll see them get sick,
you'll see them age. You'll see them have diarrhea and vomit.
If you're unlucky, you'll see their insides someday during surgery.
Don't kid yourself that it's
worth hurting other people
to get the most beautiful woman or man possible. It's not worth it.
It won't last. It's great to be in a relationship, but have it with the right motivation.
Next.
If you have anger issues
or you get upset quickly,
then fantasize about giving that person
something they would like to have. It's  called maitre
jampa
love.
Fantasy, try to remember how nice it is to give someone
something they love, something they want.
Try to have that attitude.
If you don't feel friendly towards the other person, then
fantasize about doing a meditation
on giving them something they really like.
Next.
I'll give you a minute on this. I'm sure you don't remember what that is?
Tim cheats by looking ahead.
What was that?
It's about pride.
Pride will also be an obstacle to fulfilling your vows.
And... one of the most common types of pride
in the monastic environment where this book was typically taught
is how much you know about the scriptures, how many facts you've collected
over your life. What
I really like is the obscure facts of the Dharma
and the more you collect,
the more you feel like you're special.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, "The whole  All the Dharma you have ever studied in your life, all the things you have memorized,
all the things you have debated about,
all the Geshe degrees you have ever been able to obtain
– you know nothing compared to what remains to be learned.
You are like a worm at the bottom of the ocean
that sometimes comes out and looks at the stars.
Many of these stars are surrounded by planets.
There are people on these planets.  There are things you need to know about these people.
There are things that we know,
that we are so proud to know,
that are a tiny, very tiny part of what you might know.
So there is no need to be proud.
Next.
One of the main motivations not to break your vows
or your commitments, your morals, which will stop you from achieving nirvana, which will stop you from achieving the second
level of lamrim is personal nirvana;
This is the understanding of emptiness, the study of emptiness.
If you understand that the bad things
others do to you
stem directly from what you did last week,
then you won't make big mistakes.  The more you can study emptiness,
the more you can study cause and effect, dependent origination,
which means this person comes from my seeds,
the easier it will be to keep your commitments.  The easier it will be.  So study, study, study.
I had a teacher, an old Mongolian spiritual teacher, very old, sick with tuberculosis, and
he often said,
"You are very good. You are so proud, you feel great pride about Princeton and
then the Geshe degree,
it is very useful, very useful...
you will try even harder
just to look smart.
That is good, but later try to give it up.
Just learn to be a good person."  It's very funny
He gave me Adam's text on his deathbed.
I remember this.
Next.  Is
this technically the fourth reason or not?  No.
One of the reasons why you break your vows or lose your commitments.
It is very difficult in today's world to
remember your vows when you are very busy.  When everything moves very fast.
There are a thousand things to find on the internet
and life moves so fast.
It is difficult to maintain this self-awareness;  Do
I break my vows, do I do anything to harm others?
You need to slow down a little, go back to your vows,
and maintain some conscious sensitivity
to the fact that you have obligations not to harm other people.
The more things you have to do, the more attentive you should be.
It's even easier to get annoyed with your partner when you're very busy.
They're trying to tell you something and
you have 10 things to do at work and you're like,
"I don't have time to listen right now.
My boss gave me 10 things to do."
These are the moments when you must slow down
and return to your vows.
Don't forget your commitment to be kind to other people, even when you are under
a lot of stress and are very busy.  It
is better to break a few business commitments than to be
nervous and irritable and not be kind to people,
better to not pay a bill or miss a business meeting or
not do as good a job as you can
if it means keeping your mind clear.
Next picture.
This is a woman buying a useless thing in a store.
Try to remember this story.
She said, "Oh, this box is so beautiful."   She went to the department store.  She bought this.....
....what is this thing from the home decor store, the
place where you shop?  Box and Barrel.
She went to the Crate and Barrel in America.  She said, "Oh, my husband will love this box."
She has no idea what she'll use it for,
but she's taking it home.
Then when she gets home, her husband will say, "You're crazy, that's a useless little box.
We have enough junk in the house. Take it back. Give me your money back."
Should she go to the gas station and try to return it?
No, that's not where she got the box from. This seems obvious, but we have to say it.
If you buy a stupid box
because you like it and you think your husband will like it and he doesn't...
and he talks you into taking the box back.
Don't take it back to the other place. Take it back to where you bought it.
What does that mean?
You guys have to pay me.
When the time comes to confess
that you broke the vow,
try to go back to the person who gave you the vow.
Try to confess to the person who gave you the vow. Is it okay
to confess to yourself at home?
In general, not for vows that you took from other people.
If you haven't taken the vow
from someone else, then,  Maybe you can
confess at home to a Buddha statue or something like that, in extreme cases that's okay.
But in general,
if you can go back to the person who gave you the vows
and confess to them openly, don't be ashamed. We're shameless all day long.
So be shameless with your vows and say, "What the hell?" -
go straight to your teacher and tell them you broke this stupid vow.
And your teacher will say, "Wow, you're really a bad person. You're like that, yeah, yeah."
Get it over with, and then you'll feel so pure, you'll feel good.
You can be ashamed of a lot of things in your life, but don't be ashamed of your vows.
If you break a vow, go and tell somebody,
and that's how you get rid of it. You get rid of the problem.
If you hold it in and hide it, and if you do more to hide it than to confess
or keep it in, then it's just stupid
and you won't feel good. You don't  you will feel pure.
Just be open with your teachers. I have this problem. I have this bad habit.
Karma is destroyed, the seed is destroyed.
Your teacher will say, "I've heard this before, you told me this before." But be persistent and keep telling them. The
next picture.
It's about... wait, do you remember?
Again, it's about honoring the
small details of the vows.
These are actually vows for monks, they had to brush their teeth, with a
stick called a so shing,
it was a stick that you had to use to brush your teeth,
you just cut it from a tree and you use it.
It's a toothbrush.
It said that monks had to have their own toothbrushes, and you have to brush your teeth.
It may seem like a small thing.
"Wait, I'm trying to keep my tantric vow to go to Amitabha's paradise
and protect all sentient beings," and the Buddha says, "Yeah, but for now,
could you just brush your teeth  "Every day?"
You might think, but it's not such a big vow.
But it's the little things that make up the Buddha's paradise.
It's the little things that bodhisattvas do
that are pleasing to other people.
Of course, everyone in the world is going to...
...stop a nuclear war or whatever if they can. I mean, that's obvious.
But are you a good enough person
that you don't even want people to smell your breath.
Maybe it will hurt them?
If you're very sensitive
to little things that could hurt other people,
then we can say that you're keeping your morality.
And then, it's the little details that put the finishing touches
on your Buddha's paradise, which you see in the next picture.
This person is decorating a Christmas tree...
If you've ever decorated a Christmas tree, but those of us who grew up in the Christian tradition,
our parents made us decorate Christmas trees.
There's something cool about
hanging the last ornament.
Everyone looks at the tree and says, "Done?"  and then they say, "Yes, it's all ready."
And he says, "Wait, there's one more ball we have to hang right here."
That decorating the Christmas tree
is brushing your teeth. It's the little finishing details
that you add to your Buddhahood. It's the little things that make Buddhas. It's
not about the big things. It's not about the big things. It's paying attention
to the little things
to make other people happy that makes Buddha.
Next.
See if you remember this. I'll give you the key - yamantaka, yamantaka.
It's a famous lamrim story.
Monks and nuns are supposed to practice Sojong twice a month and admit
the mistakes we've made to each other
and openly.
The teacher said,
"...they hit the 'gandhi' stick."  They hit the "gandi".
It's a special piece of wood, it looks like a 2x4
and you hit it with another stick and it makes a sharp, dull sound...
and it's an ancient bell before metal was common.
They hit the board and when you hear it
you should go to Sojong.  They still do it.
I made the "gandhi" stick with my teacher.  He wanted one like this for himself
and we made it in the right size.
Here are all these rules.
When you hear the blow of the gandi stick
you have to....hold it here..
You hold the gandi stick here and you hit it like this.
Then all monks and nuns must come to confession.
This teacher says, "Hey, they hit Gandhi. Let's go."
The student replies, "No, I'm not going to confession today."
The teacher asks: "What?"
It is one of the main obligations of a monk to practice Sojong.
The teacher asks: "What are you talking about?"  The student replies: "I don't have to go today."
The teacher says, "What do you mean you don't have to go today?"
The student replies: "Have you forgotten that yesterday you gave me the Yamantaka empowerment?
I am Yamantaka, I am Buddha. I don't need to go to Sojong anymore."
The teacher grabs him by the ear and says, "What the hell, are you Yamantaka?
Yamantaka will come with me to Sojong right now."
This means – don’t tell me that you are a great tantric,
and you don’t need to observe morality
and now you have a higher vision –
this is a completely wrong idea!
If you have received secret initiation,
then you must do Sojong or something like that every morning.
You must practice more than others.
Because that's what gives you...
gives power to your tantric practice.  Be kind to other people
and admit when you make a mistake.
Next.
This is a sad picture.  We always think of morality as the basis of
our practice, the foundation of our practice.
Pabongka Rinpoche sort of turned this around.
This is a perfect picture.
He said, "Imagine an apple tree
that someone has divided in half. Actually, they used a palm tree.
Someone divided it, and they cut off the top of the tree.
So you won't have any leaves, not
even a single leaf will grow.
So you won't have any flowers.
So you won't get the fruits that always come from flowers.
You won't get anything.
A person who is not kind to other people, day after day, hour after hour,
they are depriving themselves of any chance of
getting these beautiful fruits from the practice.
Next.
This was an idea about something my teacher asked me...
Sorry, I asked my teacher, and I don't know if you remember, but I asked him.
The first of the five paths, the path of accumulation,
you attain it when you have personal tragedy,
but if you are on the bodhisattva path,
you attain it when you get bodhichitta.
I asked, "I don't understand, what is tragic about bodhichitta?
And he said, "No, no, no.
It's still the theme of tragedy.
It's just the tragedy of every living being, every being in this entire universe,
is experiencing the same tragedy."
This common tragedy is the beginning of the five paths.
Thinking about this tragedy
is the beginning of the five paths for the bodhisattva.
So it's actually the same thing.  The
puppy is having trouble, but now all the puppies in the basket are having trouble.
We are all in this together.
And this is the beginning of bodhicitta.
Next picture.
This is a guy shaking hands with someone in his office.
I suppose the lady is introducing them to each other.  This is Joe, he works in the advertising department,
and this is Sam, he works in the computer department.
They shake hands.  Do
you remember what this is?
It was a really, really cool exercise where we had to close our eyes
and think about the person who irritates us the most.
And see if we can get upset.  The problem with this kind of practice is that
after about 10 minutes you forget that it is a practice.
And you really get upset!
Let's see if I can get upset.
How are you going to do this?
I'm going to think about this guy who gave me trouble this week.  "Okay, go ahead."
Then slowly the man begins to tremble.  You say, "What's going on?"
"I was upset."  The experiment was a success.
If this is your lama, they will say,
"Look how you feel when you first start thinking about this person.
How do you feel? What's going on in your heart?"  I
don’t know about you, but I have a little lump in my heart.
I'm starting to feel some discomfort here or there.
When I think about a person who is bothering me or about a problem that is bothering me,
I can deliberately build up tension
within myself.
He says, "Let's do an exercise - let's try to create some tension in your heart,
then look at that tension and recognize it, as if you were shaking someone's hand.
Find out what it feels like
when a mental cloud, a negative emotion,
appears in your heart, and keep practicing this.
Once you feel better and you've forgotten about that person,
then think of them again.
See if you can get upset again.
See if you start getting upset again.
Try to get familiar with what it feels like; shake hands: 'Hello.'  This is Geshe Michael."
"Hello.  "What, what's your name?"
"I'm starting to get upset with this man."
"Nice to meet you.  Now I know what you look like.
Now I can look after you.  I can avoid you in the future."
Next.
It's called "journey to the center of the sun."
The theme of this lamrim was - Love in the Time of a Virus. A
virus is a big thing, it's spread all over the world.
I've lived a long life and I thought I've seen it all.
I turned 60 and I thought nothing new would happen now.
I'm quite prepared for anything that can happen.
I've seen everything, and nothing can upset me too much. Then this virus comes along and threatens everyone in the world.
It's a big thing that covers the whole planet.
I don't know if this has happened to you, but it has happened to me.
This is probably bad deed number nine, which is ill will;
being happy when someone has problems.
When I heard about famous, annoying people getting sick.
I didn't want them to die or anything, but...
...I said it's bad to be bad.
And then I caught myself thinking about it. It
feels like a big thing. It
feels like,  that this problem has spread all over the planet.
It feels like I'm having a hard time dealing with it.
We've just started,
after 10 years of studying in lam-rim,
we've just entered the path of people with great abilities.
We're going to open this teaching
with the idea of ​​bodhichitta. What is bodhichitta?
It's not the enlightened mind. Forget this lousy translation, incredibly bad translation.
It's the wish that I could become a Buddha to help countless sentient beings.
There is a direct experience of this,
just as there is a direct perception of emptiness.
There are parallel experiences that
we have to have in this life, and again, you have to be in meditation.
We're describing an extraordinary... what do you call it?... breakthrough.
The experience of the threshold of entry,
when you enter a deep state of meditation.
Because time and space come from seeds,
if you can deal with these seeds,
then you can compress time and space.
In a meditation that lasts no more than half an hour.
You can actually meet
every person in the universe,
including  animals and insects, birds and fish.
You can talk to each of them individually,
for half an hour.
You can make a commitment to each of them.
You meet with them, you see that each of them is suffering,
each of them is going through a difficult life and is worried about the future.
You can go to each one individually and say,
"I'll take care of everything, calm down."
I worked when I was at university.
I got a scholarship, but they told me I had to work a few hours a week. It
turned out to be 30 hours a week.
I had to drive a truck.
Actually, at first they put me in the cafeteria and said you will be mopping the floor in the cafeteria.
I quit within 10 hours. I quit on the first day.
Then they said you can drive a truck. I said, this is fun. I will drive a truck.
I drove a truck for five years.
We had a guy, a
regular at the university, named Big John.
His name was Big John. He's Polish, seven feet tall, a huge guy.
All  They were afraid when they saw him.
They were afraid of him, but he was a very kind person.
He brought donuts to work and was from Trenton, New Jersey.
He did the nicest things for us and covered for us. One time we wrecked the truck.
We crashed the truck into a tree and broke it in half.
He covered for us: "Oh, those bolts weren't tight enough.
I don't know what happened.  The truck fell apart.  Don't blame these guys.
Don't blame these young guys.
They're just drivers."
Then he winked at us and said, "I've got your back.  I've got your back, guys."
I always think of him when I think about bodhichitta.
You'll meet every living being in the universe face to face.
And you'll say, "Big John's got your back.  I've got your back.  Don't worry."
Don't worry about it. I've got your back.
That's bodhichitta. You have to have that experience.
You have to work for that experience. You have to meditate.
You have to study bodhichitta. You have to
study the lam-rim about bodhichitta.
You have to do all these steps;
exchanging yourself for others...
One day you'll have that experience and meet every living being.
You'll tell them, "I've got your back." Don't worry. I've got your back."
Big Mike will take care of you, or Big Tim, or Big Saiji.  Do
n't worry.  Do
n't worry.  I'll take care of it!
It's exactly what it sounds like.  This is a personal commitment.
Why are we talking about this?
You will do this for countless worlds.  When you do this, the day you do this,
you will be doing this for countless worlds.
An action that is performed directly on every living being in countless worlds will have
no problem taking care of one virus in one world.
It's nothing.  A
virus that puts
7 or 8 billion people at risk is nothing compared to bodhichitta.
We said, if you spill ketchup on your shirt
and you take that shirt into the middle of the sun where it's 25 million degrees Fahrenheit, the
ketchup stain will probably come out.
You probably don't need to worry about the ketchup stain.  Work on your bodhichitta.
You will destroy the virus, inadvertently, by accident.
Nothing special.
Next picture.
Don't get involved with other paths.
Learn bodhicitta.  Learn to gain this experience.
Don't waste your time.
Don't focus on other things.  Focus on bodhichitta.
Then you won't have to do things twice.
We were talking about when things are done twice.  This lady is in a great hurry.
She says, "I don't have time for this bodhicitta.
I'll go straight to tantra."
You will still have to go back and pick up the thing you forgot,
namely, bodhicitta.
First, work on your bodhichitta.
You don't have to go home, pick up bodhichitta and come back.
Next we had a radical example in the next idiom.
She is difficult to remember.  I'll give you a second to think about it.  I
don't know if you remember this.
It's quite complicated.
A group of 60 boys and girls were going to achieve nirvana by simply seeing emptiness directly,
without bodhichitta, this is the lower nirvana.
Manjushri appears and teaches them bodhicitta.
Maybe he talked about this experience we just talked about.
They were all irritated with Manjushri.  They're like, "Don't waste our time.
We're close to nirvana. We can feel it. We can taste it.
We've all seen emptiness before, don't waste our time.
Don't talk to us about it."
Because they did not respect the teaching of bodhichitta,
they went to hell.
They did not reach nirvana.  They fell into the realms of hell.
But they burned everything
and they became people again after many millions of years.
Deep within them was this teaching that Manjushri had given them about bodhichitta, and they remembered it.
They became bodhisattvas and became Buddhas.
It will take less time than
achieving lower nirvana without studying bodhichitta.  It would be
faster to go to hell
and come back
and start all over again with bodhichitta
if you didn't use bodhichitta
and ended up in lower nirvana.
This is an image of someone deliberately sending someone else the wrong way.
This lady asks,
"Where is the super highway that leads to the store I want to visit?"
The guy knows the highway is closed.
He tells her: "Don't turn there, the highway is closed. You need to go the other way."
And she insists: “No,
tell me where the highway I need is.”
Then he deceives her
and says: "Take this path."  This is actually a long way that he proposed one way or another.
This is a story about clever means.
Next picture.
This is a warm-up before the race.
What do we usually use this image for?  Do you remember, guys?
This is a breathing meditation.
We usually say that breathing meditation is just a warm-up.  Don't think it's a race.  There is
no pre-race stretching competition at the Olympics.
This doesn't happen; they don't give a gold medal for stretching.
In this case, we are not talking about breathing meditation.  We are talking about the fact that
it is good to do the three main paths in order.
To grieve for this world.
Strive to directly gain this experience of bodhichitta.
See the void so you can help everyone.
Do a warm-up with the first feelings of sadness about this life.
Next picture.
We're almost done.  I think we are very close.  Are we close yet?  Not that close.  Okay,
you remember who these guys are, they are a very disgusting company.
I guess you see them in shopping malls or somewhere else singing bad songs.
They are called "prelude".
Steps on the path for practitioners of lesser ability;
who are trying to achieve a higher rebirth.
Steps on the path for practitioners of average ability
who try not to return to this world at all.
Steps on the Path for Practitioners of Great Ability.
These two levels are just a prelude.  The
most important thing is to achieve bodhicitta.  What is higher than bodhicitta?
There are six perfections.  Check again:
steps on the path to avoid falling into the
lower hell realms, steps on the path to attain nirvana,
and then we get bodhicitta.
This experience of meeting every living being
and making a commitment that I will take care of you.  There are
six up here.
This is six in Chinese.
Here are six perfections.
So what is the most important thing from this?
Which one is a real group?  What prelude?
These guys, obviously, lower nirvana is not that important.
Interestingly, Pabongka Rinpoche says
that this experience
with every living being is the
main action.
This is what I want you to focus on.
I want you to try to get this experience.
If you have this experience, we can talk about the six perfections,
including number six - the vision of emptiness.
Let's talk about this later.
Come on, I want you guys to focus on this experience.
By the way, a good way to get this experience is to imagine the experience and try to listen to its description.
Pretend you can do it and keep pretending.
Keep doing this.
It looks like a slot machine.
I like to compare it to a slot machine.
When you click on a slot machine,
pictures, cherries and other things start popping up
.
Not that I've ever played a slot machine... Well, once, with my dad.
You press the lever and then these dials start popping out.
Just imagine
your mother's face appearing.
You say, "Mom, you look worried."  She's like, "Yeah, I'm worried about life."
You say, "Don't worry, Big John's got your back.
Just calm down. I get it. I'll take care of you."
Then your father's face appears.
Not just a picture, but a person appears.
It's like meditation.  Try to imagine this.  Try practicing this.
This will trigger something very important.
This will trigger something very important.  Introduce people one by one.
See how they feel.
Make a commitment.  Don't worry.  I've got your back.  I will take care of you.
Then they leave.  Imagine another person.
Practice this way.  You can do five or six people.
It will happen faster because time will change.
Pabongka Rinpoche says this is the main show.
This is the Rolling Stones.
The rest are just new bands that aren't very good.
Who's at the end?  Do they have a final act?  Usually not.
Anyway, the rest of them just leave the stadium or something.  Do not worry about it.
Now we move on to
10 cool things that will happen to you if you have bodhichitta.
We will only have time to do the first one in this lamrim.
The first cool thing about having bodhichitta is...
if you were a nerdy kid
who played tennis in school.
Your dream would be to be on the team.
Next picture.
Yes, Geshe Michael is standing in the center.
Above, not down there.
You can be on the team.  It's great to be on a team of bodhisattvas.
Work in this team.
It's so cool to be on this team
because this team spans the entire universe.
These are all the cool people in the entire universe.  It's nice to be part of this team.
This is very nice.
This was the first benefit of bodhicitta.
Next picture.
This is a guy visiting an art museum.
He spoke of two levels of tantra;  The first level is meeting with angels, the
second level is learning from them how to be an angel and how to become an angel.
On the first level,
we must actually meet
real angels in person.
It's not like standing in an art museum and looking at a statue or thangka of a person.
This is a meeting with a person directly and this is a completely different matter.
If you try to practice tantra
without this experience of bodhichitta, it will be like looking at images of Buddhas
instead of meeting Buddhas.
They don't like to talk to people who don't have bodhichitta.
They feel more comfortable
around people who have had this experience.  Try to get this experience.
Then tantra will work for you.
If you don't have this experience,
tantra will be difficult.
It will be like looking at pictures of Buddhas instead of hanging out with Buddhas.
Next.
If you try to practice tantra without bodhichitta, you may get bad results.
We talked about the first nuclear test
in our time.
Scientists have acknowledged that this explosion
could have burned down the entire world.
They were just trying to do something cool.
But they risked a huge disaster.
This is tantra without bodhichitta.
It would be like accidentally setting the entire sky on fire.  You'll ruin everything.
Next.
Even a small amount of neutral karma
will become powerful for a person with bodhichitta.
A person with bodhichitta can feed a bird,
pray about it,
and it touches millions of people.  They have this power.
Next picture.
Even small bad actions, such as stealing French fries to give to a bird, can become positive if performed by a bodhisattva.
But this is a dangerous practice.  We are not at that level.  We are not at that level.  We are not at that level. Did
you hear that?  No?
We had a photo of a
puffer fish.
People in Japan, such as macho men, eat this fish.
It has very, very poisonous parts that can kill you instantly.  In Japan, 50 people die every year.
But people still go to the restaurant.  To serve this fish in a restaurant,
you need three years of special training, otherwise you'll kill someone.
It's like stealing French fries to give to a bird
because you want to help the bird.
We are not at that level.  Do not attempt to eat pufferfish unless you are trained.
Then we had a nice photo of Nick and Erin
with their big boss,
Amelie.
Amelie represents Buddha,
Nick
represents the father
which is bodhichitta, and Erin represents wisdom
which is the direct perception of emptiness.
In a certain sense,
for some reason I don't know what kind of belief it is in Asia, but in a certain sense the father is irreplaceable.  There is something
special about this father.
I don't know what this is.  But still...
Emptiness can be seen on different levels,
on all three tracks.
But bodhicitta, you have to be a special person.
You can only see it on the highest track.
This defines you
as a person on the top track.
You need both to have a child who is a Buddha.
Next picture.
We said @
Which Tim identified correctly today.
What is your main practice?   What is most important in your life right now?
Until the next lamrim, the Medicine Buddha lamrim...
....I want you guys to consider this as your main practice.
Try to have this experience of meeting countless beings.
Try to get this experience.
I don't care if you sit for hour after hour and nothing happens,
just try, just pretend.
Scroll this through your mind until the next lamrim.
Let's make a deal like this.  Make this your main practice.
Next picture.
If this practice were not so important, then one of the greatest Buddhists of all time, Lord Atisha, would not have sailed to India for
13 months, risking his life, to receive the teachings on
bodhichitta that you just received
in this video.  And you didn't have to go anywhere.
If Atisha thought it was worth risking his life for 13 months
on a tiny ship,
in the Pacific and the Indian Ocean, then maybe
it matters, maybe it's worth it.
Next picture.
I think the stupidest thing you can do in your life is to go to Paris and not buy a croissant.
Fine.  I'm just saying that there are probably other stupid things you can do in your life.
But for me it would be absolute stupidity to
go to Paris and not stop by a bakery.  At least
buy a pancake
on the street
with... what is this chocolate thing?
Nutella, yes.
Not trying a pancake with Nutella.
Going to Paris and not trying a Nutella crepe is proof you're crazy.
If you study lamrim,
if you have advanced this far in lamrim, and Geshela has been teaching it for 10 years,
you have finally reached the croissant,
which is the bodhisattva experience.
Don't go crazy and leave Paris without eating it.  Do not leave lamrim without having this experience.
You will be a complete idiot.
We're done with the croissant.  I think you want to give a presentation?
No, I assumed there might be a croissant in this bag?
Tim Lowenhaupt
is going to do the official presentation
for Heschel, at my expense,
Oh, is that kraussan?  What do you call it?
What is it called?
Kraussan with chocolate!  (Pain au chocolat) You have to cut it into three pieces.
And give me all three, that is, no, just one.
I got a chocolate croissant.
This is what you give to your teacher when he teaches you bodhicitta.
Let's make a deal.
Work on this experience for the next couple of months.  Do the dedication chapter in your Shantideva meditation.
Try to work on getting this experience.  The worst that can happen is that at least
you will have planted the seeds in your mind to have that experience.
Just pretend.
Just sit and fantasize about it.  Fantasy is a good meditation.
Imagine that you had this experience of meeting,
one after another,
every living being.
You make a personal commitment with each of them
to take care of them fully,
Excellent.  See you in the next Medicine Buddha lamrim.  Hooray!